all right so during this afternoon's
class two things are going to happen the
people from other countries are going to
take a nap jet lag it's so nice to see
you have jet lag jasmine it makes me
makes me very happy now you know how I
feel and the other people are going to
study how to do the retreat that starts
on Monday afternoon okay
so the purpose of this session is to
talk about how we're going to what are
we going to do during the retreat okay
three days retreat okay so how many
people did retreat here before how many
people didn't do return here
I mean this reach me oh my gosh maybe I
should skip it okay
well I'll teach you the meditations
anyway move so if you want to you can
follow I'm going to I'm going to just
look at the schedule okay and I'm
looking I guess it's in here you've got
a copy of the schedule okay
so Monday we have a our fourth class
together well the fourth Laura in class
at 4:45 we finish then we have about 15
minutes to pee-pee then at five o'clock
on Monday in the afternoon we'll go to
the jetsam couple Center and we will do
the closing of the retreat borders okay
and then after that you shouldn't leave
the retreat area okay and nobody should
come in unless they're on the stuff
there's a list of people who can come
and go in every retreat
okay if someone breaks the boundary who
is not scheduled to break the boundary
retreating okay so you make a promise to
stay if you can if you have a medical
emergency you should grow okay some kind
of emergency you can go but otherwise
you should decide after that ceremony
that you're in the Dharma Jail and you
can't get out okay I'd rather he treat
finishes okay you make a commitment I
remember when I did my three-year
retreat we had a gate where the cars
went through and I remember closing the
gate for the last time and I closed the
gate and I said okay three years three
months three days I won't open this door
I won't touch this gate again and we we
did a good retreat we kept it very
strong how many people in this room did
three we three-year retreat one two
three four five six seven eight nine I
think so you're very lucky to have them
with you people who have done a
three-year retreat can you raise your
hands again and if you have a question
about retreat or you're not sure about
something then talk to them okay talk to
one of those guys okay they have a lot
of experience they did a thousand days
of silence mostly and and they know how
to do retreat so I think Donna Mountain
has two precious things one is the rocks
we have lots of rocks and people used to
find heart-shaped rocks here and take
them and give them to myeloma and in
finding one that he said no more
heart-shaped rocks we have lots of rocks
and we also have I think you know one of
the most one of the largest groups of
people who did through your retreat in
the in the world is here so there's nine
people in this room you can talk to and
ask them if you're having a problem or
you have a question that's the that's
the really important resource here at
Diamond Mountain and director and his
wife who I'd like to say Michael and
Melissa can you stand up they're also
very special because they did through
your retreat so they they understand
retreat center they understand how to
run a retreat so we're lucky to have
them very lucky to have them running the
place so well and thank you for that I
think most of you know but I think it's
good to say it again that the people who
did the first tree or between on this
land they each built a cottage with
their own money okay and before they
started building they signed an
agreement or they agreed that when they
finish their retreat they would give the
retreat cottage to Diamond forever so
other people could do retreats here for
many generations so when you stay in a
cabin here it was built by and they
built their cabins with their own hands
and it was very difficult really
difficult in the Sun here and they
worked really really hard they used
every penny they had they went into
retreat they were broke so I like to
thank them for the cabins also yes
okay
so we'll close the border at five
o'clock if the ceremony mainly take half
an hour or something like that and we'll
do it in the Jetson couple Center
because it's good to face the border so
we'll save that front gate of Diamond
Mountain and we'll do the traditional
clothing ceremony during that ceremony
mainly we ask one spirit protector to
help us her name is Kendall oh he and
she's like Dharma bodyguard for you and
she will protect the boundary okay so
she has special powers and you have to
be sweet to her like she likes to have a
tormal for a bribe to guard the border
and you have to do a ceremony and you
have to tell her how beautiful she is
and how smart she is and then she said
okay I'll help you all and she protects
the border okay so that ceremony is
mostly to ask her to protect the border
okay and and those ceremonies are
important you shouldn't do a retreat
without doing those ceremonies I when I
was younger a hundred years ago I didn't
like all these ceremonies and I tried to
do a retreat without them and I got a
lot of trouble okay and so I learned by
having problems that you have to follow
these rules you should ask Kendall order
to protect the retreat you should do the
correct ceremony you shouldn't make a
last-minute cheap offering like potato
chips or something she doesn't like for
10 cents
she likes really good cakes and stuff
and it shows respect for her and so you
shall respect offered us and then during
the retreat you keep at Orma on your
altar and that's to her to to honor her
and to thank her for working for you
that's her salary instead Toma okay and
you keep it nice okay sometimes we keep
them in a big jar if you find that you
have bugs getting into your tour Mars or
something like that you can put it
inside a jar upside down and like that
then that evening which will be around
6:00 to 7:00 in your own cottage okay
you should put protection markers up on
your house okay and it's tradition to
walk out of the front door of your
retreat cottage go to your left okay and
don't put the marker first on the door
put it on the wall to your left outside
okay outside the wall okay so you have
for protection markers you walk out of
your cottage and you turn left and then
you put it on the first side wall okay
got it
so here I don't know let's say we walk
out of that door is your front door the
first protection marker goes on this
wall on the outside I like to put it on
the window because it sticks better you
can use tape or you shouldn't fall down
it's bad luck and it kind of breaks the
border so you could tape it three four
times it doesn't matter okay on that
side then you go to the back put it on
the outside another one and then you go
to the this side put another one okay
and then the last one it's like you're
getting into a submarine you know you
back up and you put the normal marker on
the
during your close the door and then
you're in the Dharma submarine hitting
then you're protected okay so it should
be like that then we have a mantra we're
going to do okay
there's to guide the mantras secret
mantras and open mantras and this is an
open mantra so everybody can do it
without an initiation which is a big
major way and some coppice mantra okay
so couple lived about six hundred fifty
years ago and he's in some kind of
strange person like very very unusual
well the most unusual person on this
world and he just like explained
everything perfectly and unbelievable
and I can't really convince you by
saying but it's true
so I've studied a lot of different
traditions you know I learned meditation
from Goenka personally before you were
born
okay not you okay
and so I understand the Southern
tradition you know from that and and
then I I spent a long time studying the
text about things like Maha mudra or
zouk 10v parson ah I studied them a lot
you know and then I met some copper and
there's nothing like that nothing close
you know it's a million miles away from
everything else you know and I don't
mean to criticize the other traditions I
learned a lot from Glinka but it's
nothing like to a couple not close
nothing close did silk change stuff
nothing close not even not a million
miles close
and and it's just something you need to
study a long time before you can
understand it you have to read many many
scriptures right now I'm reading the
greatest scripture from early China
because it was translated into Tibetan a
thousand years ago more than a thousand
years ago it's available it's it's the
greatest early Chinese commentary to the
citrus which is by a student of chuan
song called the USA yeah and it's
unbelievable it's it's 2,000 pages long
and so god bless teachers respected it
so much they put it in the tenure it's
in the Tibetan Buddhist books and they
translated it and now the Chinese is
some of its gone but we have the whole
thing in Tibetan language from the
Chinese it was written in Chinese and
it's part of our Kenya it's part of our
ancient books canon you know so I kind
of have a feeling for how Buddhism
started this commentary is 700 years
before some couple and it's it's great
but it's not like um come on you know
it's great it's beautiful I would like
to teach it some time in China maybe
that would be cool okay and it's easy to
read it's not difficult to we can do it
something we can do it but when you read
some cover
it makes takapa used it also some cop I
used the Chinese commentary by UN say he
used it in his writings in so if you do
them together it's unbelievable it's
just unbelievable so anyway if if we
could absorb what tsongkhapa thought
which takes a whole lifetime
you definitely could see emptiness
directly and I don't think you could see
emptiness directly with those other
things I don't think it's possible I'm
sure it's not possible so to do is
monter is something wonderful it's great
to have its mantra mantra means you're
calling some cop that said please help
me to understand emptiness help me to
practice help me to be a good person
help me to do everything I do with an
understanding of the second husband it's
basically that it's not different from
that and you won't see the second
husband explained in those other
traditions they don't understand it they
don't have it they never got it and
that's Buddhism that's real Buddhism so
and that will help you the most
so anyway dude its own cup of mantra
it's on page
everybody in this room if you're going
to do a retreat you should have this
book okay it's called three treasures
there's a joke in English don't leave
home without it okay it's a three
valuable retreat tools you should have a
copy Tim will sell you one if you don't
have one it used to be $30 I guess the
Chinese was $10 extra just kidding
printing cost okay sorry we don't make
any profit from these retreats we lost
money very well on 25 retreats so don't
worry about it it's really free it's
better than free we're paying you to
come so get this book get one today if
you don't have one you can't do retreat
without it Tim has copies if you can't
afford it he'll pay for it we'll pay for
it and get one okay and have it with you
okay now there's numbers
because when we add different
translations there's more pages so we
can't use page numbers we use section
numbers okay and there's section numbers
in each of the three books in here okay
so section number ten in the middle okay
which is the part about tsongkhapa's
practice that's the mantra for jets on
copper okay and you should learn them
that's the mantra you're going to do I
don't know ten thousand times or
something
okay I don't know how many months as you
did in your three-year retreat do you
remember do you remember I was like ten
million or something it wasn't Jerome
you don't remember I don't know let's
see it for something like ten thousand
or something it's okay I think we get
about a million in in my three-year
retreat something that so anyway you
keep your maintenance you can say it in
Chinese you can say it in afterwards
doesn't matter
in Spanish Jetta copper will understand
because he's a Buddha so you can say it
in you can even say it Stanley can even
say it in Cantonese good boy and he was
still understanding so it doesn't matter
you said in your own language and do the
Montaigne your own language next time
you can do it in English you can do it
in Canadian what's this about a boot
this is sort of mantras boot okay and if
you just say much so really what we're
doing is a mountain retreat and don't
waste your time when you go for a lot it
means every day generally two million
and exhibit about question Jason I
detailed out which copy you have right
page 113 maybe well really no anyway
you're finding me mates away 13 January
think you making me wrong but that man
to Pomona tonight oh my god okay and
just keep doing it when you go for a
walk
except when you in the bathroom remember
Terry told me I couldn't do in the
bathroom but that's the main practice
the meaning of the mantras you're just
saying be kolcaba help me to understand
emptiness tell me to be a good person
okay like that all right
humidity retention and the meaning of
the mantra is here okay you can study it
all right then on on that night Monday
night the first session after you okay
the morning normally for most people the
morning session is great it's clear the
afternoon session is so-so
the evening session is hopeless okay so
we get shorter the long session is in
the morning and then you start to get a
little sleep in the afternoon and in the
evening
the minute you start doing your mantra
you feel sleepy okay so that's a
shortest one okay so follow the schedule
okay some people's biorhythms what it
called a Dietetic cycles circadian
rhythm yeah that's awesome if they're
different you know if you're a night
person then you can you can change the
schedule okay you don't have to stick to
the schedule
but if most of us stay to the same
schedule there's an energy of
I'm doing the same thing together at the
same time so I encourage you if it feels
okay follow this schedule because then
we'll all be doing some couple Mondays
at the same time I'll be doing moment
you're at the same time and there's an
energy to that okay alright but you
don't have to if you have a different
body clock you do it your own way
that's okay alright there's a 45 minute
meditation at 8:30 okay
and that's sort of optional because
you'll be really sleepy alright try to
get up on time 6:30 on Tuesday then at 7
o'clock on Tuesday just recite the
Georgia Georgia is the meditation song
it's the first work in the three
treasures okay it's called Georgia means
meditation some preparation and it was
written by Pablo impetus la Mer okay and
it's very very famous into intimate okay
so go through read it out loud it's
supposed to be a good love to read it
out loud because all the spirits can
hear you so you're supposed to read it
loud enough that you can hear it okay so
you can have a soft voice but someone
sitting right next to you should be able
to hear it
okay if you want okay if you prefer to
read silently that's okay it's alright
they are all Buddhist they can read your
mind
they don't have trouble to hear you okay
so if you want to read it in your mind
that's okay okay then if you find a
section in the Georgia which is sweet to
you and you want to stop and hang there
for a while it's okay so the practice is
more important than the schedule okay
like if you get to the part where you're
filling the sky with flowers and you
start to go crazy go ahead go crazy do
flowers for 45 minutes okay that's fine
all right
if you find something that you really
get into then don't feel obligated to
finish the Georgia okay if you find
something sweet stay there for a while
okay and then get up you know try to not
leave the llama hanging like bring them
back in here okay put them back in your
heart like don't forget them if you
feeling the sky with different flowers
for 45 minutes come back to the llama
and park them here okay in a sugar
crystal okay inside a sugar okay 8:15 oh
sorry
7:30 after the Georgia after - R Georgia
by the way you can't finish the Georgian
half an hour
finish what you can tomorrow you can
pick up at the same place if you want
okay
eight o'clock sorry 7:30 7:30 you start
your meditations from this book there
are 27 long rain meditations then
there's a meditation about dying how to
die by the way if you don't learn
anything else at these larvae and
retreats if you learn how to die
properly it's worth it all the money
spent all the jet lag you got if if you
can learn to die properly it's you it
was worth it these 25 retreats all the
work to prepare them it was worth it so
I thought it would be nice if you had it
in a book so you could do it at home my
lama asked me to do it every night so i
did coffee meditation and death
meditation okay and you try to get to
emptiness okay and we'll do it together
I'll do it with you maybe this afternoon
how about right now in case we die in
case there's an earthquake
okay there's never been an earthquake
here Brandon let's do that meditation
okay this is just meditation going into
emptiness meditation okay we all got
together on Easter whether Easter that
was so sweet and we did a death
meditation together and then we came out
of it just like Jesus and that's really
cool okay here we go get ready to
meditate okay what's the first step yeah
especially me
okay I like the system in Guadalajara
they charge you $50 if you if you're if
your phone goes off during the minutes
at group meditation then it goes off
everybody goes like they pretend it's
not their phone
okay you ready
ahh blow your nose anybody need
emergency equipment
cocking around I like to blow my nose
during the teaching because it wakes up
the people watching it on the knowledge
base six months from now they're like
okay ready
okay sit like a rock sit like a rock
rocks don't open books and things like
that
everybody has to die normally if they
don't practice well enough everybody has
to die and during the death process
there's a special opportunity to see
emptiness directly so the purpose of
this meditation is to practice what it
feels like to die until you get to the
point in death when you have a window of
opportunity to see emptiness if you know
what you're doing if you don't it'll
just pass and you will be reborn
someplace so here we go come watch your
body
sit up straight pull in your stomach
slightly and keep it there just a slight
pressure
relax your eyelids small Mona Lisa smile
[Music]
fingers are relaxed shoulders are
relaxed and pulled back shoulder blades
together in the back
brighten up your forehead relax it
release it open it and don't punch it up
when we start focusing keep it light and
your eyelids are super relaxed if you
feel sleepy you can crack your eyelids
open but don't look
it relaxed the corners of your mode and
then slowly come to your breaths like
getting in the saddle of a horse this is
you're getting into the saddle of your
meditation come to your breath and start
focusing on the long exhales so the
inhales will take care of themselves or
else you're dead already
and milk slowly naturally comfortably
start to follow with accounting each
exhale is one next exhale is two and see
if you can stay with your breath sliding
in and out without thinking about
something else just be here you're stuck
here for a week you can't go anywhere
no use to worry about your job or your
family or the world or what to Trump do
this morning just forget it for a week
and come to your breath that's all
you're supposed to do
and imagine where it is you might be
dying in this life if you died this
month next month where might you be I
think my child will probably be on my
bed at home you know I would die it in
my home so think about that Dad and
imagine you're lying in it something
happened you got hurt in a car accident
or something happened in yard you are in
your last few minutes in this world
you're on the bed and you will not get
off at the better life
you are looking out and close friends
close family are with you some can be
holding your hand some are holding your
feet they might be crying they don't
want you to leave and you don't want to
move but it doesn't take you
your fingers are getting a little cold
hard to move them your feet feel cold
very hard to breathe not easy to get air
through your nose or through your mouth
families talking softly but it's getting
difficult to hear what they're saying
you call this almost all the way up your
legs and arms
can't hear the family anymore can't move
your I'm sorry make anymore your mouth
closes and your nose your nostrils shut
inside and you start breathing can't
breathe and your mind your consciousness
starts to withdraw from the world your
eyes closed for the last time you can't
open them you would like to buy your
kids
and the thoughts withdraw into the
middle of your mind and you're alone and
they start and it's silent in suddenly
it's as if you're walking I like to
picture myself close to those big
mountains in Diamond Mountain behind the
retreat Valley I'm walking down the
bottom part going downhill and then
suddenly the pieces of rock huge pieces
of rock the site of your retreat cottage
the size of cars are are breaking off
the mountain rolling down the mountain
you can see if you look at that mountain
sometime you can see where pieces of
rock like that have come down you can
see the path that follows and they're
crushing everything in their path and
you are running you start to run ahead
of this huge boulders were rolling down
the hill behind you the noise is
terrible like a many car accidents at
the same time and you're running the
earth element is collapsing inside of
you
then suddenly behind the mountain comes
a huge tsunami wave like the one that
took Japan and it's moving very fast
huge unbelievable unimaginable almost
blocks out the skies and you're hopeless
in front of it and you're running as
fast as you can not the wave catches you
and throws you into the water you are
fighting just to get some more breath
you are surrounded by huge ways you are
in the water
struggling being dragged down and I I
personally when I do this meditation I
think of Diamond Mountain I'm being
pushed by the waves down into the valley
here past this temple and I'm just
fighting to try to get some breath some
air and I just to make the meditation
easy the visualization easier for me I
imagine it carries me out 1012 miles
through blue and to the other side is
just flat desert then the water element
has dissolved and you're just laying
suddenly the water leaves you in the
desert and the water drains away and
you're calling across the desert and the
Sun comes up very very large filling
most of the sky like no normal Sun
and fire element in your bodies is
dissolving and it feels terrible heat it
feels like being inside of a fire then
you are crawling imagine crawling away
from buoy across the desert fire all
around me then the fire starts to wear
out and then this huge wind storm comes
across the desert like a singapore
hurricane tearing across the desert and
it's tearing at your body things are
flying past your trees rocks dust the
wind is tearing at your body this is the
wind element is dissolving and then
suddenly that starts to dissipate and
your I imagine standing walking slowly
ahead no place to go just alone in a
empty landscape and I'm walking ahead
and far away I can see a mirage and
these are the subtle elements of your
body are breaking down and you see way
in the distance you see like it looks
like a leg shimmering but it's just
a mirage when you walk towards it
and you get closer and closer and you
actually walk through the Mirage and on
the other side in the other land it's
all just like fog or smoke you are
walking through dense smoke or fog
there's nothing you can see in front of
you if you put your hand out in front of
you you can see everything is thick fog
smoke you are walking still hopelessly
driven to a head to the smoke and then
you start to see sparks in the smoke
they say like fireflies or sparks from
some machines and you can see sparks
here and there in the air in front of
you and around you these are parts of
your consciousness are breaking down as
you go deeper into death
then ahead of you you can see a very
steady fire flame like a candle flames
so the world is getting smaller your
world is shrinking it feels like you're
going through a tunnel which gets more
and more narrow and at the end of the
tunnel in the dark you can see a single
candle flame in mobile it's it's burning
but it's not moving there's no win just
a steady unmoving candle flame when
you're walking towards this flavor and
then you actually walk through the flame
because you're only small now your world
is very small and on the other side of
the flame it's just black everything
around you total black and still you're
walking
and then somehow the blockage deeper
deeper blood than the one before so try
to imagine it deeper blood all around
you like ink and then suddenly you're
into a deeper deepest black total
darkness you can't see your feet you
can't see your arms
you can just see darkness total complete
darkness
it's still walking
then slowly in the horizon and for me I
like to imagine the east side of the
retreat Valley those of you who do the
three-year retreat when the Sun daybreak
comes before sunrise
Thursday break before the Sun breaks the
horizon then to the east there's this
white color of the sky before the yellow
comes there's a white and that white in
some of you behind the horizon if it
begins to spread all around you and you
are surrounded by white light
and you're still walking
and then our red light like a sunset
starts to replace the white light and
you are walking through a world of red
light
and then slowly the red light dissolves
and you come to another darkness black
deeper black very deeply then suddenly
things change and it feels like you're
walking inside of crystal like dirt or
crystalline feeling to the to the world
around you you are surrounded in the
kind of crystal er the the air is
crystal like diamond as if you're
walking to diamond but you can breathe
and you can walk but the world around
you is like diamond and in this point of
death
your central channel is broken open all
the chakras have broken open
and the brown is flowing freely with no
obstacle at this point you your physical
body releases peepee poo-poo but your
you're not aware of it because you are
deep deep deep inside and at this point
you can grab this small few minutes of
opportunity to think about emptiness you
can think about how nothing you see is
not coming from you everything you see
around you everything you're
experiencing every thought every feeling
in this moment is coming from seeds in
your life and there's nothing around you
which is coming from the outside it's
all coming from inside you so cancel the
idea that anything's happening to you
it's all happening from you and hold on
and we'll stay here for a few minutes
try to stay in the feeling that
everything you thought was there coming
from its own side never was in that
emptiness
then you can start to come out of that
emptiness I like to come out standing on
the sky as a Buddha and I'm suddenly
come out of there not not to rebirth but
I come into a Buddha in understanding
above a planet looking down
maybe it's nighttime and it looks
beautiful with all the lights of the
cities this is the world that I have to
take care of and be there
serve them guide them I like to stand
there with my teacher who in in the
diamond right teachings Mariana it's my
partner in the mirror
sorta like mommy and daddy looking at a
world thinking we're going to take care
of it
then follow your brats for three breaths
3ds XL to get ready to come up just
relax don't get it you know too excited
about coming out then slowly open your
eyes on the last inhale take a stretch
it's good when you meditate to take
stretches that's what yoga was
originally for right
any questions no
when does the class egg when does the
cloud sunny with Windows it in sync ok
hang on a second we got a microphone
here then everyone can hear
thank you okay my question is about kind
of about the onionskin and the layers
because I think in our system the center
is seeds right in the center of the
onion and then I don't know I just was
thinking about the emptiness of my own
body during this meditation and that the
heart suture came up there's no part of
you that sees there's no part of you
that's aware of what you see and say
that again there's no part of you that
sees there's no part of you that's aware
of what you see isn't that in the heart
suture so I and in the different school
say the center of the onion is awareness
I in are says seeds could you talk about
that well all the experiences that you
have in the death process are coming
from seeds and they're always the same
so some people say if things are empty
they should always be different you know
like Neil Young song everyone hears it a
different way so it seems like if things
are empty they should always be
different to different people and
because we always say oh that that
dinner you cook last night that proves
emptiness you know she loved it and she
hated it so that presenting us you know
one thing is experienced in two
different ways according to the seeds of
people but given all the possible
combinations everyone always has the
same experience when they die so people
always go through the same slow seeds
the pattern in which seeds are collected
throughout your life always ends this
way they always create this dissolution
process the same way so it's still the
case then you the things you're
experiencing and your awareness of them
are coming from your seeds
yeah
yeah of course yeah if it's an existing
thing it's coming from seeds some people
then have a problem with emptiness
because emptiness doesn't change the
house can it come from seeds you see and
then the classic answer is like the
water in a fountain
it's the seeds are producing an
unchanging form you know it looks like
it still looks like a fountain but it's
a it's a flow of seed creating the same
outline you know sound like that any
other question I have a question in the
crystal that appearance it is part and
now I think and I think everything is
come from me I'm wondering at that
particle I think oh yeah you're going to
her question is you know how can I have
like complicated thoughts in the middle
of dying you know like I'm dying
things are crystal how can I pause and
think oh gosh like let's do this and
then guess I said you don't matter who
you know because your mind is dissolving
that's why we have to practice it many
times that's why we do between so it
becomes instinct it becomes natural you
don't think about it okay
so if you do it many many times you know
that's the purpose to do a retreat you
get used to it and then when it really
comes you say oh I this is what Gitchell
are took me through all next is going to
come the fireflies oh there they are you
know and then that's what that's called
getting ready for death nema so it'll be
burned into your mind
it'll be automatic like Vivian - dancer
first time you down to dance you can't
remember left foot right foot three
steps four steps my dance teacher gave
up on me but if you dance many times
many times the same danced in it you
don't think about it so the word in
Sanskrit for meditation is Bhavana in
Tibetan is comb which means get used to
it it becomes natural it becomes
automatic or next I'm going to see the
the red eye oh there is my mirror it's
kind and nice it's going to get black oh
there it is you know yeah just like they
said and the crystal is difficult okay
the crystal is like in the art in the in
the scripture it says think of an autumn
a Harvest Moon
okay and how it makes the darkness of
the sky no crystal so it's a very
delicate thing it's not like a window
it's a crystalline quality to an autumn
night okay you gotta cook that any more
questions
you
Thank You geisha that I could my
question is actually about the crystal
part when we arrived to that section of
us I mean I imagine everyone can see
that crystal right whether they've
meditated or not
right yeah everyone goes through it so I
like to call it the stop on the subway
it's like you're stopping at 4th Street
in the New York subway
you got you got three minutes to you
know then the subway goes to a bird or a
dog or and you know and then you got the
door opens and you got like two minutes
to see something and if you don't see it
the door shutting and you go to Brooklyn
so so that's like that's actually the
second part of my question how do you go
into seeing empty do decide do you just
like thinking about during the retreat
you're going to say okay and by the way
don't take a long time on the getting
there I mean just keep moving steadily
because what you'll learn if you do a
three-day retreat is that the the real
sweet spot in meditation is amazingly
brief you know you you're in retreat for
a whole day and you maybe have 15
minutes of super sweet spot and you
gotta use it so the minute you hit your
sweet spot like rush everything up and
get to the crystal part and I put
photographs in here for you and I'm not
really happy with some of them I worked
really for a long time on it but uh
there's a it's a page fourteen and again
you can memorize the photos and then you
don't have to look at the book you know
but not not in the meditation but when
you actually die well when the real
thing up yeah how do you start
perceiving indirectly tonight
remembering it it's all it's more than
memory it's it's like body memory when
you get a dance many times or the way
you drive your car you don't think oh
I'm going to move my hands and left I'm
going to move my hand to the right it
becomes automatic when you drive for a
few years you you can talk to somebody
and your hands are on automatic pilot so
that's why we have to do the meditation
many many times my lama asked me to do
it every night for many years because he
wanted me to get used to it so of course
you got you're going to come up to this
you're gonna come up against this thing
in Buddhism where your Lama told you to
do 26 things just before you go to bed
and so you have to be reasonable you
know don't get anxiety attacks trying to
do everything your Lama said to do
before you go to bed you know just calm
down let some things go you know
geshe-la gave us ten things to do before
you go to bed I'm tired I'm falling
asleep now pick one off sleep you know
don't have an anxiety crisis don't let
Dharma become another thing to be
anxiety about okay like just take it
easy okay I'm not going to dynamite
I mean I'm not going to do my death
meditation tonight I'm going to do it
I'm tired I feel like a little coffee
meditation light coffee meditation and
it's the same with retreat you know many
more people have an anxiety crisis
during retreat than the people who are
lazy lazy people about 20% 80% are
worried they're not doing enough and
then they ruin their meditation Cazale
I'm not doing enough you know I'm in
retreat I'm supposed to be in line yeah
and I just feel tired
okay so done you know don't press it too
hard
but the idea is to the best thing for me
when I do long retreat yourself I make a
hot cocoa I sit in a chair I curl up you
know in my heart conk on and I do a
little coffee meditation and it's
perfect okay like you don't have to be
at you know mine o'clock it's not going
to happen so I just curl up with a hot
cocoa and I do my coffee meditation baby
yes so the main thing in me treatise
don't waste your time but but most
people have anxiety during metrio I'm
not I didn't get enough mantra stunners
nothing's happening I didn't see any
Buddhist this afternoon you know so just
realize the main thing is to think how
lucky you are to be here how lucky are
someone built this place and these crazy
people live here and take care of it you
know god bless them and just relax and
have a good time okay okay I want to do
some more of the meditations so that's
the dying meditation and I'd like to go
we have another half hour right do you
need a pee-pee break yes or no yes okay
let's take a 10-minute pee pee break
okay but please come back at five four
zero five forty okay be sitting down
quiet at five forty and we'll do 20
minutes more
[Music]
meditation number five page three
meditation number five page three okay
by the way I'm going to again the plan
is I'll go over all the meditations with
you then you'll do your three-day
retreat and then as we go through the
scripture you'll see them coming up but
maybe some of them don't come up till
after you do your retreat I have to
teach you all the meditations first
meditation number five refers to Sangha
Joe
we finished Buddha Joe this morning we
talked about Buddha jewel
we finished Dharma jewel Dharma jewel
means understand the pen is Dharma jewel
very simple understand the second
husband is damaged or if you think about
the second husband when someone gets mad
at you
you have taken refuge and you're a
Buddhist okay there now there's one more
refuge which is Sangha jewel okay so
what's a Sangha jewel it's people
understand the pen it's the community so
real
the real division in in this world is
not between ordained people and non
ordained people it's not that people who
wear Rev robes are Sangha stop talking
back there it's not the case that people
who wear red robes are the real Sangha
and the rest of us are not Sangha that's
that's not the real division the real
division is who understands the pen and
who doesn't understand the pen who
understands the second husband and who
doesn't understand the second husband
people understand the pen people
understand the second husband they
automatically become a community in the
world
okay well
they're from Guangzhou or Jaipur I don't
know
Indus River Valley or our mantra Bull
Durham lived in the only town in the
world that sounds like a Smith and it
doesn't matter where you're from okay if
you understand the pin you're part of
that club and if you don't understand
the pen you're not part of that Club
okay so Sangha means people with eyes
okay that's the meaning of meditation
number five
meditation number five is called a
person with eyes and heart heart means
they care about you they love you they
want you to come live in this town
called Sangha okay they want you to be
part of that town so they run around the
world repeating over and over the pen
every time they get a chance let's try
the other way I have to pass for me okay
one more time what's this big yeah pen
if a dog come in here and taking it in a
goal they see it as a chew toy okay
who's right the human or the dome yeah
why they can use it now they can use it
it's okay dog can't you enjoy human says
why are you chewing on my pen dog says
why don't you enjoy to you okay it's
equal okay then if I put it here all the
people go out all the dogs go out at
that time it's at pen or chew toy
nothing yet okay then if the dog comes
back
first it becomes a to time if the human
come back friends it becomes a pen
therefore the pen is coming from my mind
not from the pen okay there's something
from my mind okay
what there's a seed opening in my mind
okay who put the seed there yeah only I
can put a seed in my mind okay how I
shared a pen with somebody yeah okay or
I shared my tutorial with someone okay
can I put a seed in my mind then when I
look at this thing Tenshi dopant in my
mind small picture comes out it becomes
a pen
okay now and then the four steps I can
get anything I want with the four steps
there's a guide named there's a company
called spiritual gangster they make your
because they started with two people
near here in Phoenix just a man and his
wife and they started with nothing
nothing recently they were interviewed
on the morning good morning she'll or
whatever I never I don't have a TV for
half an hour a free free interview on
the most important morning show in the
United States half an hour they
explained why they're now the most
successful yoga clothing company and
they said it's this thing called the
four steps and they explained it on
American television to a whole country
you know for half an hour they gave them
a half hour which is usually the
interview there's three minutes four
minutes they talked for half an hour
then he came back I had dinner with them
I said congratulations you know that's
amazing that they said guess why we
didn't they what you told us to do and
then he says K star can I ask you a
personal because I said yeah he says how
come your students don't do it
I said I don't know okay he actually
tried it and he runs his company that
way and he only uses the four steps and
they got very famous now and they're
doing really big they got bigger they're
in bloomingdales now and big big company
now and so it it's exciting
hark means share it with other people do
it yourself share it with other people
okay
you have eyes which is your knowledge of
the pin and then share it with other
people I can't get I'll have to get the
dog to get the other one okay all right
so meditation number five
think about Sangha I want to be Sangha
what Sangha jewel okay I'll tell you
something cool if you understand
emptiness okay I mean up until recently
Buddhism was the biggest religion in the
world there were more Buddhists than
anything else okay if China is Buddhist
is the biggest religion in the world
it's 1.4 billion people you know we got
Erin else out number okay so up until
now I mean pretty much it's the biggest
religion in the world one point four
billion people minimum right something
like that don't count the American
Buddhists okay 1.4 billion people
they were mostly historically they are
Buddhists okay then every morning
they're supposed to get up and go double
budaya normal done my anomaly they're
supposed to take refuge right I you know
sang Gala gives us you're sure the cats
with you
kendama kept secure Buddhists everywhere
are praying every morning to the three
jewels okay now I'll tell you something
cool if you understand the pants they
are praying to you
and that's cool right 1 billion people
asking you for help every morning ok
then you are Sangha yeah a Sangha jewel
ok so anyway that's somebody also during
this meditation think about who's Sangha
jewel think about your Sangha jewel okay
think about being the person who
protects other people by teaching them
about the second husband that protects
you from unhappiness okay so you are
some dad you'll think about it
spend some time on it okay be be happy
be proud okay by accident you heard
about the pen then suddenly you got to
be a very VIP Dharma VIP you know now
you're like very special person because
you can really help people okay you
teach people the four steps you're like
I don't know it's like you're creating a
world you know a whole planet you see if
you teach anybody the four steps and if
they like this guy if you ask in that
guy's name is Ian if you ask him are you
a Buddhist I think you say no but but
he's he took refuge he's using the first
death and it works for him then it's
cool okay then you're Sangha jewel and
think about it and I think it's great
that we call the New York center three
jewels it's cool we even gotta the web
address right because it was so long ago
and we should thank any Thomas she comes
back de-clutch okay so during meditation
number five we're going to think about
how I'm the summit you'll and be in this
meditation you should feel some kind of
healthy pride
like James Brown said I'm so cool I
could kiss myself so just in this
magazine you're supposed to be like yeah
I'm pretty goddamn cool I understand the
pen I can help people I got something to
share okay be happy this meditation is
100% narcissistic you like I'm so cool
okay
all right number six then you know how
do you know you're a special person okay
like meditation number six how do you
know you're a special person because you
know the diamond color sutra or you know
the heart sutra you met it in your
lifetime okay you met the diamond color
suit in country you met him in your life
okay then you must be amazing you must
be special okay because you made it you
made the diamond color Sutra you made
the Heart Sutra you know you can't go
home ever again and say I'm not very
good person I'm not very special person
you know I'm always sad and unsure of
myself I have anxiety all the time okay
that's true
but you're also special because you met
you created the Buddhism on this planet
you created chicken gym you created
ching ching you created DCI you created
diamond mountain it's all come from you
okay so have a little appreciation for
yourself okay
that's meditation number six the fruits
of a visit which is the name of
meditation number six it means we don't
live in a time when we can meet the
historical Buddha Gautama Buddha left
this world okay but we can enjoy the
fruits of his visit
okay we we have the Heart Sutra we have
the diamond cutter Souter we have a
tradition which has not been broken for
two and a half thousand years okay y'all
got order to the gala you to the
ordering of your mug also to another
dimension to what them something to you
so that we every two weeks we recite the
lineage you are part of an unbroken
lineage okay
that the teachers are there it's never
been broken you are part of it you're
the next link in an unbroken chain since
the buna okay then be a little happy
about yourself okay and the fruits of a
visit means the the fact that you have
the heart sutra the fact that you have
the diamond cutter sutra in your world
is the is the fruits of lord buddha
coming here okay honey so proof that we
are blessed so these two meditations
meditation number five where you
understand you are the summit jewel the
meditation number six where you
understand you had enough karma to live
in a world where Buddhism is still alive
these two meditations are supposed to
make you happy about yourself and your
life okay
so if you do these two meditations well
when you get up out of that meditation
you should like Swagger a little bit
like oh yeah oh cool yeah you know you
should be a little happy about your life
okay because only one creature in a
billion can have the Heart Sutra
or Democrat suit okay you are special
you are special you are extremely rare
in the universe okay
you are at the top of the food chain
Dharma food chain you know you're up
here you know you have all these
teachings you have the pen you have the
four steps okay you your extraordinarily
special in the universe you are the most
special people in universe you got a if
you succeed at meditation number five
and number six you should come out of
your you know get up make lunch like you
know I'm pretty cool actually
okay you should feel happy okay okay I'm
going to do number seven because I guess
I'll do some more tomorrow okay but
number seven as we will see in the
lamrim scripture I was in Thailand you
know descent in December right and we
were studying refuge so I gave refuge
vows for the first time in many years I
think maybe 20 years or something to a
large group and everybody was excited it
took me many many nights to do the name
and you know I ain't get much sleep
and Stanley adamyourself they're all
going you know we didn't give Sleeman
everybody was so happy and they got that
refuge vows and they got an explanation
of them
and by the way we're going to do that
again in the scripture but everybody
felt like oh i know i'm i got my
buddhist name you know I'm a I took
refuge you didn't you did not okay
that's not resi okay refuge is when
you're sitting on the couch with your
wife or your husband and they start
yelling at you and you remember the pins
okay and and a bunker in p'chai says in
the lamb rim okay you didn't get refuge
when Geshe Michael did the big ceremony
and gave you a secret name and you know
we all threw flowers or something that
wasn't the real ceremony the real refuge
vows ceremony happens on the couch at
homes when your husband says something
bad to you or your wife says something
bad to you okay you're so lucky
if your wife saw something bad here
because then you can do the real refuse
ceremony it's right there
that that that's the moment to celebrate
you know oh I took refuge what happened
my wife yelled at me I didn't say
anything because I know she's coming for
me you know oh you just took refuge
you just got your vows who gave them to
you you did okay got it
so that's the meaning of this meditation
number seven provoker Buddha says the
real ritual the real refuge ceremony
you got your holy Garmin aim on the
couch it was stupid
okay and then you didn't answer okay cuz
you understood you didn't want to see it
again next week okay and you understood
the person called you stupid wasn't
there not is okay and and that's that
was your refuge ceremony that's the
point that Popovich is making in this
meditation so when you're doing
meditation number seven I would like you
to think about bad moments in your life
five and six are supposed to make you
happy
seven supposed to make you miserable
okay oh what's the most difficult moment
I had in the last few years
oh my it was that night when my my wife
you know told me how stupid I really was
you know and then you know I felt bad
and and I felt a little angry and I felt
hurt but then I remembered that even
that person was coming from me okay like
I don't know how I planted it it's
probably a million lifetimes ago because
I'm not that mean now but uh but I was
smart I took refuge you know she called
me stupid and I didn't try to explain
myself I didn't try to prove she was
wrong I just shut up I said you know I
got a peepee I'll be bangs and I went in
the bathroom and I sat on the special
place and I I spent ten minutes thinking
about how I planted that and then by
that time I was calm and I came out and
I you know we continued dinner and
together and and I took refuge and I had
a record ceremony in the toilet
got it okay so this meditation number
seven you're going to think about a
difficult time in your life when you did
the right thing you stopped yourself
from getting upset and you said this is
coming from me it's really hard with X
my ex-husband's ex-boyfriends
ex-girlfriends I mean it's bosses okay
it's really hard if you can do it with
them you can do with anybody okay so in
this meditation pick take some of the
most tense and unhappy moments in your
life with another person and and forgive
them because they're coming from you
okay let it go because they're coming
from you and then you took refuge okay
got it
forgiveness okay all right